Chapter 44. The chart.
Had you followed Captain Ahab down into his cabin after the squall that took
place on the night succeeding that wild ratification of his purpose with his
crew. You would have seen him go to a locker in the transom, and bringing out
a large wrinkled roll of yellowish sea charts, spread them before him on his
screwed down table. Then, seeding himself before it, you would have seen
him intently study the various lines and shadings which there met his eye, and
with slow but steady pencil, trace additional courses over spaces that
before were blank. At intervals he would refer to piles of old log books beside
him wherein were set down these seasons and places in which on various former
voyages of various ships sperm whales had been captured or seen.
While thus employed, the heavy puter lamp, suspended in chains over his head,
continually rocked with the motion of the ship, and forever threw shifting
gleams and shadows of lines upon his wrinkled brow, till it almost seemed
that while he himself was marking out lines and courses on the wrinkled
charts, some invisible pencil was also tracing lines and courses upon the
deeply marked chart of his forehead.
But it was not this night in particular that in the solitude of his cabin Ahab
thus pondered over his charts. Almost every night they were brought out.
Almost every night some pencil marks were eaced and others were substituted.
For with the charts of all four oceans before him, Ahab was threading a maze of
currents and eddies, with a view to the more certain accomplishment of that
monoomanic thought of his soul.
Now, to anyone not fully acquainted with the ways of the Leviathans, it might
seem an absurdly hopeless task thus to seek out one solitary creature in the
unhooped oceans of this planet. But not so did it seem to Ahab, who knew the
sets of all tides and currents, and thereby calculating the driftings of the
sperm whales food, and also calling to mind the regular ascertained seasons for
hunting him in particular latitudes, could arrive at reasonable surmises,
almost approaching to certainties concerning the timeliest day to be upon
this or that ground in search of his prey.
So assured indeed is the fact concerning the periodicalness of the sperm whales
resorting to given waters that many hunters believe that could he be closely
observed and studied throughout the world were the logs for one voyage of
the entire whale fleet carefully collated then the migrations of the
sperm whale would be found to correspond in invariability to those of the herring
schos or the flights of swallows.
On this hint, attempts have been made to construct elaborate migratory charts of
the sperm whale. Footnote: Since the above was written, the statement is
happily borne out by an official circular issued by Lieutenant Mari of
the National Observatory, Washington, April 16th, 1851.
by that circular. It appears that precisely such a chart is in course of
completion and portions of it are presented in the circular. Quote, "This
chart divides the ocean into districts of 5° of latitude by 5° of longitude,
perpendicularly through each of which districts are 12 columns for the 12
months. and horizontally through each of which districts are three lines. One to
show the number of days that have been spent in each month in every district
and the two others to show the number of days in which whales sperm or write have
been seen. End quote. End of footnote.
Besides, when making a passage from one feeding ground to another, the sperm
whales, guided by some infallible instinct, say rather secret intelligence
from the deity, mostly swim in veins, as they are called, continuing their way
along a given ocean line with such undeviating exactitude that no ship ever
sailed her course by any chart with one tithe of such marvelous precision.
Though in these cases the direction taken by any one whale be as straight as
a surveyor's parallel, and though the line of advance be strictly confined to
its own unavoidable straight wake, yet the arbitrary vein in which at these
times he is said to swim generally embraces some few miles in width, more
or less, as the vein is presumed to expand or contract, but never exceeds
the visual sweep from the whale ship's mast heads. when circumspectly gliding
along this magic zone. The sum is that at particular seasons within that
breadth and along that path, migrating whales may with great confidence be looked for.
And hence, not only at substantiated times, upon well-known separate feeding
grounds, could Ahab hope to encounter his prey, but in crossing the widest
expanses of water between those grounds, he could, by his art, so place and time
himself on his way, as even then not to be holy, without prospect of a meeting.
There was a circumstance which at first sight seemed to entangle his delirious
but still methodical scheme, but not so in the reality perhaps, though the
gregarious sperm whales have their regular seasons for particular grounds,
yet in general you cannot conclude that the herds which haunted such and such a
latitude or longitude this year, say, will turn out to be identically the same
with those that were found in the preceding season. Though there are
peculiar and unquestionable instances where the contrary of this has proved
true in general the same remark only within a less wide limit applies to the
solitaries and hermits among the matured aged sperm whales. So that though Moby
Dick had in a former year been seen for example on what is called the sey shell
ground in the Indian Ocean or volcano Bay on the Japanese coast. Yet it did
not follow that were the Peekquad to visit either of those spots at any
subsequent corresponding season, she would infallibly encounter him there. So
too was some other feeding grounds where he had at times revealed himself. But
all these seemed only his casual stopping places and ocean ins, so to
speak, not his places of prolonged abode. And where Ahab's chances of
accomplishing his object have hitherto been spoken of, illusion has only been
made to whatever wayside antecedent extra prospects were his. Air a
particular set time or place were attained when all possibilities would
become probabilities and as Ahab fondly thought every possibility the next thing
to a certainty. that particular set time and place were conjoined in the one
technical phrase, the season on the line. For there and then, for several
consecutive years, Moby Dick had been periodically described, lingering in
those waters for a while, as the sun in its annual round loiters for a predicted
interval in any one sign of the zodiac.
There it was, too, that most of the deadly encounters with the white whale
had taken place. There the waves were storied with his deeds. There also was
that tragic spot where the monoomaniac old man had found the awful motive to
his vengeance. But in the cautious comprehensiveness and unloyitering
vigilance with which Ahab threw his brooding soul into this unfaltering
hunt, he would not permit himself to rest all his hopes upon the one crowning
fact above mentioned. However flattering it might be to those hopes, nor in the
sleeplessness of his vow could he so tranquilize his unquired heart as to
postpone all intervening quest.
Now the Peekquad had sailed from Nantucket at the very beginning of the
season on the line. No possible endeavor then could enable her commander to make
the great passage southwards double Cape Horn and then running down 60° of
latitude arrive in the equatorial Pacific in time to cruise there.
Therefore he must wait for the next ensuing season. Yet the premature hour
of the Peekquad sailing had perhaps been correctly selected by Ahab with a view
to this very complexion of things, because an interval of 365 days and
nights was before him, an interval which instead of impatiently enduring ashore,
he would spend in a miscellaneous hunt, if by chance the white whale, spending
his vacation in the seas far remote from his periodical feeding grounds, should
turn up his wrinkled brow off the Persian Gulf, or in the Bengal Bay or
China seas, or in any other waters haunted by his race, so that monsoons,
pompas, norwers, hermitans, trades, any wind but the levant and simoon might
blow Moby Dick into the devious zigzag world circle of the Peekquad's circumnavigating wake.
But granting all this, yet regarded discreetly and coolly, seems it not but
a mad idea this, that in the broad, boundless ocean, one solitary whale,
even if encountered, should be thought capable of individual recognition from
his hunter, even as a white-bearded mufty in the thronged thoroughares of Constantinople.
Yes, for the peculiar snow white brow of Moby Dick and his snow white hump could
not but be unmistakable.
And have I not tallied the whale? Ahab would mutter to himself as after pouring
over his charts till long after midnight he would throw himself back in reveries.
Tallied him and shall he escape. His broad fins are bored and scalloped out
like a lost sheep's ear. And here his mad mind would run on in a breathless
race, till a weariness and faintness of pondering came over him, and in the open
air of the deck he would seek to recover his strength. Ah God, what transes of
torment does that man endure who is consumed with one unachieved revengeful
desire? He sleeps with clenched hands and wakes with his own bloody nails in his palms.
often when forced from his hammock by exhausting and intolerably vivid dreams
of the night, which resuming his own intense thoughts through the day,
carried them on amid a clashing of frenzies, and whirled them round and
round and round in his blazing brain till the very throbbing of his lifespot
became insufferable anguish. And when, as was sometimes the case, these
spiritual throws in him heaved his being up from its base, and a chasm seemed
opening in him, from which forked flames and lightning shot up, and a cursed
fiends beckoned him to leap down among them. When this hell in himself yawned
beneath him, a wild cry would be heard through the ship, and with glaring eyes,
Ahab would burst from his stateateroom as though escaping from a bed that was
on fire. Yet these, perhaps, instead of being the unsuppressible symptoms of
some latent weakness, or fright at his own resolve, were but the plainest
tokens of its intensity. For at such times crazy Ahab, the scheming,
unappeasedly steadfast hunter of the white whale, this Ahab that had gone to
his hammock, was not the agent that so caused him to burst from it in horror
again. The latter was the eternal living principle or soul in him, and in sleep,
being for the time dissociated from the characterizing mind, which at other
times employed it for its outer vehicle or agent, it spontaneously sought escape
from the scorching contiguity of the frantic thing, of which, for the time it
was no longer an integral. But as the mind does not exist unless leagued with
the soul, therefore it must have been that in Ahab's case, yielding up all his
thoughts and fancies to his one supreme purpose. That purpose by its own sheer
ineteracy of will forced itself against gods and devils into a kind of
self-assumed independent being of its own. Nay could grimly live and burn
while the common vitality to which it was conjoined fled horrorstricken from
the unbidden and unfathered birth.
Therefore, the tormented spirit that glared out of bodily eyes, when what
seemed Ahab rushed from his room, was for the time but a vacated thing, a
formless, snambulistic being, a ray of living light, to be sure, but without an
object to color, and therefore a blankness in itself.
God help the old man. Thy thoughts have created a creature in thee. And he whose
intense thinking thus makes him a prometheus, a vulture feeds upon that
heart forever. That vulture, the very creature he creates.